Laurence A. Steinhardt Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Laurence A. Steinhardt Papers 1929-1950
MSS41301
Steinhardt, Laurence A. (Laurence Adolph), 1892-1950
42,500 items
99 containers plus 1 classified
42.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, economist, and diplomat. Correspondence, letterbooks, articles, speeches, financial papers, business records, legal papers, and other papers relating to Steinhardt's career as ambassador to Sweden, Peru, the Soviet Union, Turkey, Czechoslovakia, and Canada.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Allen, George V. (George Venable), 1903-1970--Correspondence.; Biddle, Anthony Joseph Drexel, 1896-1961--Correspondence.; Davies, Joseph Edward--Correspondence.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976--Correspondence.; Henderson, Loy W. (Loy Wesley), 1892-1986--Correspondence.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955--Correspondence.; Jackson, C. D. (Charles Douglas), 1902-1964--Correspondence.; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984--Correspondence.; Owen, Ruth Bryan, 1885-1954--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945--Correspondence.; Steinhardt, Laurence A. (Laurence Adolph), 1892-1950.; Stettinius, Edward R., Jr. (Edward Reilly), 1900-1949--Correspondence.; Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1891-1968--Correspondence.; Welles, Sumner, 1892-1961--Correspondence.
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, American--Canada.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Czechoslovakia.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Peru.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Soviet Union.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Sweden.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Turkey.
Places
Canada--Foreign relations--United States.; Czechoslovakia--Foreign relations--United States.; Peru--Foreign relations--United States.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; Sweden--Foreign relations--United States.; Turkey--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--20th century.; United States--Foreign relations--Canada.; United States--Foreign relations--Czechoslovakia.; United States--Foreign relations--Peru.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations--Sweden.; United States--Foreign relations--Turkey.
Occupations
Diplomats.; Economists.; Lawyers.
Provenance
The papers of Laurence A. Steinhardt, lawyer, economist, and diplomat, were given to the Library of Congress by his widow, Dulcie Steinhardt Beau, in 1963. Additional material was given by the American Jewish Archives in 1983.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Laurence A. Steinhardt are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified materials.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1892, Oct. 6 Born, New York, N.Y.
1913 A.B., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1915 M.A. and LL.B., Columbia University, New York, N.Y. Admitted to New York bar
1915 1916 Accountant
1916 Counsel to Waslaw Nijinsky
1920 1933 Member, Guggenheimer, Untermyer and Marshall law firm
1933 Member, Executive Finance Committee, Democratic National Committee and Franklin D. Roosevelt's pre-convention campaign committee
1933 1937 Ambassador to Sweden
1937 1939 Ambassador to Peru
1938 Delegate, Eighth Conference of the Pan-American Union, Lima, Peru
1939 1941 Ambassador to USSR
1942 1945 Ambassador to Turkey
1945 1948 Ambassador to Czechoslovakia
1948 1950 Ambassador to Canada
1950, Mar. 28 Killed in an airplane accident
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Laurence Adolph Steinhardt (1892-1950) span the years 1929-1950, with the bulk of the material focused on his career in the State Department from 1933 until his death in an airplane crash in 1950. Included are correspondence, memoranda, reports, legal and financial records, speeches and writings, printed matter, and miscellaneous material relating to his positions as ambassador to Sweden, Peru, the Soviet Union, Turkey, Czechoslovakia, and Canada.. The papers are organized into five series: General File; Subject and Legal Files; Letterbooks; Addition; and Classified.
The General File (formerly titled Miscellaneous) constitutes the bulk of the collection and consists largely of incoming correspondence, embassy reports, writings, and personal material organized by year. The papers also contain personal financial material, files relating to the day-to-day operation of the various embassies to which Steinhardt was assigned, and a small number of articles and speeches.
Included among the many notable correspondents in the collection are George V. Allen, Anthony Joseph Drexel Biddle, Joseph Edward Davies, James A. Farley, Loy W. Henderson, Cordell Hull, C. D. Jackson, Alfred A. Knopf, Ruth Bryan Owen, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Edward R. Stettinius, Arthur Hays Sulzberger, and Sumner Welles.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
General File, 1932-1950
Subject and Legal Files, 1933-1945
Letterbooks, 1929-1950
Addition, 1930-1948
Classified, 1947
Container List
- General File, 1932-1950 (Box 1-66)
  Correspondence (largely incoming), memoranda, reports, financial papers, drafts and printed copies of articles and speeches, clippings, cards and invitations, and printed matter.
  Arranged by year and therein alphabetically.
  - 1932 (Box 1)
    - General correspondence (Box 1)
    - Articles (Box 2)
    - Financial papers (Box 2)
    - Financial papers (Box 3)
  - 1933 (Box 4)
    - General correspondence (Box 4)
      - A-M (Box 4)
      - N-Z (Box 5)
    - Speeches and articles (Box 5)
    - Embassy papers (Box 5)
    - Financial papers (Box 6-7)
  - 1934 (Box 8)
    - General correspondence (Box 8)
      - A-L (Box 8)
      - M-Z (Box 9)
    - Speeches and articles (Box 9)
    - Miscellany (Box 9)
    - Financial papers (Box 10-11)
  - 1935 (Box 12)
    - General correspondence (Box 12)
      - A-R (Box 12)
      - S-Z (Box 13)
    - Speeches and articles (Box 13)
    - Financial papers (Box 13)
    - Financial papers (Box 14)
  - 1936 (Box 15)
    - General correspondence (Box 15)
      - A-O (Box 15)
      - P-Z (Box 16)
    - Financial papers (Box 17-18)
  - 1937 (Box 19)
    - General correspondence (Box 19)
      - A-S (Box 19)
      - T-Z (Box 20)
    - Financial papers (Box 20)
    - Financial papers (Box 21-22)
  - 1938 (Box 23)
    - General correspondence (Box 23)
      - A-R (Box 23)
      - S-Z (Box 24)
    - Speeches and articles (Box 24)
    - Financial papers (Box 24)
    - Financial papers (Box 25-26)
  - 1939 (Box 27)
    - General correspondence, A-Z (Box 27)
    - Financial papers (Box 27)
  - 1940 (Box 28)
    - General correspondence (Box 28)
      - A-O (Box 28)
      - P-Z (Box 29)
    - Financial papers (Box 29)
    - Financial papers (Box 30-31)
  - 1941 (Box 32)
    - General correspondence (Box 32)
      - A-R (Box 32)
      - S-Z (Box 33)
    - Financial papers (Box 34-35)
  - 1942 (Box 36)
    - General correspondence (Box 36)
      - A-M (Box 36)
      - M-Z (Box 37)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 37)
    - Financial papers (Box 38-39)
  - 1943 (Box 40)
    - General correspondence, A-Z (Box 40)
    - Papers regarding (Box 41)
      - U. S. embassy in Turkey (Box 41)
      - Alice Leone Moats (Box 41)
    - Medical information regarding Steinhardt (Box 41)
    - Financial papers (Box 42)
  - 1944 (Box 43)
    - General correspondence, A-Z (Box 43)
    - Articles and other material, regarding Middle East reports on War Refugee Board and evacuation of Jews from Europe (Box 44)
    - Embassy papers (Box 44)
    - Financial papers (Box 45)
  - 1945 (Box 46)
    - General correspondence, A-Z (Box 46)
    - News reports (Box 47)
    - Embassy papers (Box 47)
    - Cards and invitations (Box 47)
    - Financial papers (Box 48)
  - 1946 (Box 49)
    - General correspondence (Box 49)
      - A-O (Box 49)
      - P-Z (Box 50)
    - Speeches and articles (Box 50)
    - Cards and invitations (Box 50)
    - Embassy papers (Box 50)
    - Financial papers (Box 51-52)
  - 1947 (Box 53)
    - General correspondence (Box 53)
      - A-P (Box 53)
      - Q-Z See also Classified (Box 54)
    - Cards and invitations (Box 54)
    - Speeches (Box 54)
    - Embassy papers See also Classified (Box 54)
    - Financial papers (Box 54)
    - Financial papers (Box 55)
  - 1948 (Box 56)
    - General correspondence (Box 56)
      - A-K (Box 56)
      - L-Z (Box 57)
    - Speeches and interviews (Box 58)
    - Embassy papers (Box 58)
    - Financial papers (Box 59)
  - 1949 (Box 60)
    - General correspondence (Box 60)
      - A-I (Box 60)
      - J-R (Box 61)
      - S-Z (Box 62)
    - Speeches and articles (Box 63)
    - Embassy papers (Box 63)
    - Financial papers (Box 63)
    - Financial papers (Box 64)
  - 1950 (Box 65)
    - General correspondence, A-Z (Box 65)
    - Embassy papers (Box 65)
    - Financial papers (Box 66)
- Subject and Legal Files, 1933-1945 (Box 67-70)
  Memoranda, reports, legal and financial records.
  Arranged by topic.
  - Russian conditions, 1933 (Box 67)
  - Madeleine S. Partridge will, 1934 (Box 67)
  - Kreuger affairs, 1934-1935 (Box 67)
  - Sweden, 1937 (Box 67)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1945 (Box 67)
  - Czechoslovakia and Poland, reports and clippings, 1947 (Box 67)
  - Richard Hofmann estate (Box 68)
  - Marguerite Herczeg estate (Box 69)
  - Martha M. Hall estate (Box 69)
  - Elliott and Dowling trusts (Box 69)
  - Stockholm Enskilda Bank, correspondence and cancelled checks, 1933-1937 (Box 70)
- Letterbooks, 1929-1950 (Box 71-88)
  Bound volumes of carbon copies of outgoing letters.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1929-1930 (Box 71)
  - 1931 (Box 72)
  - 1932 (Box 73)
  - 1933 (Box 74)
  - 6 July 1933-1 Apr. 1936 (Box 75)
  - 12 Feb. 1936-29 July 1938 (Box 76)
  - 14 July 1938-3 Feb. 1940 (Box 77)
  - 5 Feb. 1940-29 Dec. 1941 (Box 78)
  - 20 Jan. 1942-31 Dec. 1942 (Box 79)
  - 8 Dec. 1942-30 Mar. 1945 (Box 80)
  - 12 Nov. 1943-26 June 1944 (Box 81)
  - 2 Apr. 1945-30 Dec. 1946 (Box 82)
  - 2 Jan. 1947-20 Nov. 1947 (Box 83)
  - 1 Jan. 1947-31 Jan. 1949 (Box 84)
  - 1 Jan. 1948-31 31 Jan. 1950 (Box 85)
  - 1 Feb. 1949-21 July 1949 (Box 86)
  - 6 Aug. 1949-31 Oct. 1949 (Box 87)
  - 1 Nov. 1949-5 Apr. 1950 (Box 88)
- Addition, 1930-1948 (Box 89-99)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1948 (Box 89-95)
    Family, personal, and general correspondence.
    Family letters are arranged chronologically; general correspondence is arranged alphabetically.
    - Family, 1933-1946, undated (Box 89)
    - General (Box 89)
      - A-By, (5 folders) (Box 89)
      - C-G, (5 folders) (Box 90)
      - H-L, (5 folders) (Box 91)
      - L-Q, (5 folders) (Box 92)
      - R-St, (5 folders) (Box 93)
      - Sm-W, (6 folders) (Box 94)
      - W-Z, (2 folders) (Box 95)
      - Unidentified (Box 95)
  - Embassy Papers, 1934-1948 (Box 95)
    Correspondence, speeches, writings, clippings, and miscellany.
    - 1934-1948, undated See also Classified, (3 folders) (Box 95)
  - Speeches and Statements, 1933-1946 (Box 96)
    Speeches, statements, and related correspondence.
    - 1933-1948, (3 folders) (Box 96)
  - Financial Papers, 1930-1948 (Box 96-99)
    Business, financial, and legal papers.
    - 1930-1934, (4 folders) (Box 96)
    - 1935-1938, (6 folders) (Box 97)
    - 1939-1947, (8 folders) (Box 98)
    - 1948, undated, (2 folders) (Box 99)
  - Miscellany (Box 99)
    Newspaper articles, clippings, and unidentified and undated material.
    No arrangement.
    - Miscellany (Box 99)
      - Newspaper articles, clippings, and unidentified and undated material, (4 folders) (Box 99)
- Classified, 1947 (Box CL 1)
  Correspondence.
  Arranged and described according to the series, container, and folder from which the items were removed.
  - General File (Box CL 1)
    - 1947 (Box CL 1)
      - General correspondence (Container 54) (Box CL 1)
      - Embassy papers (Container 54) (Box CL 1)
  - Addition (Box CL 1)
    - Correspondence (Box CL 1)
      - Embassy papers, 1947 (Container 95) (Box CL 1)